<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The abuses of the Romish church anatomised. By a vvelwiller to Sion, and to all them that loue the truth in the truth</title>
            <author>Catholic Church.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107868</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843560</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843560</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8303</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8303)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 684:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The abuses of the Romish church anatomised. By a vvelwiller to Sion, and to all them that loue the truth in the truth</title>
                  <author>Catholic Church.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Augustine Mathewes, and are to be sold by John Grismand at his shop in Pauls Alley at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: 'Anonymus'.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A1) B-C (-C7-8).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8303:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8303:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ABVSES OF THE RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISH CHVRCH ANATOMIZED.</p>
            <p>BY A Welwiller to Sion, and to all them that loue the Truth in the Truth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Religio a Chriſto religat Romana: ſubinde</l>
               <l>Aes religit; rectos &amp; relegare jubet.</l>
               <l>Viuere qui ſancte cupitis diſcedite Roma,</l>
               <l>Omnia cum liceant, non licet eſſe bonum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Auguſtine Mathewes,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>John Griſmand</hi> at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Alley at the Signe of the Gunne. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8303:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8303:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, (for ſo I will ſtile thee, till I find thee contrary) The intolerable abuſes of Pole-ſhorne Popelings, haue in all ages heeretofore, and are ſtill ſo great, that many haue been animated, (I had almoſt ſaid inforced) thereby to ſhew themſelues in Print, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe neuer meant it, if they had not been inſtigated thereto by their abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Lying, Whoring, Swearing, Blaspheming, Pride, Drunkenneſſe, Couetouſneſſe, and the like. I my ſelfe am one of this number; I haue heere
<pb facs="tcp:8303:5"/>publiſhed a Booke, the firſt which euer yet ſet forth, and ſhall be the last, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe this find kind entertainement. If then (gentle Reader) thou accepteſt willingly and louingly, what thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt laid downe plainly and rudely, the Authour will acknowledge himſelfe bound to pleaſure thee in what hee is able; if otherwiſe thou play the Crit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, carping at euery thing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing that ill which was intended well, doe as thou pleaſeſt, vſe mee as thou wilt, I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine as thou vſeſt me, ANONYMVS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8303:5"/>
            <head>THE ABVSES OF THE ROMISH CHVRCH ANATOMIZED.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Their Lying.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Vguſtus,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Tryumph which he made of <hi>Marke Anthony</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> brought with him to Rome a Prieſt, of Egypt, aged threeſcore yeres, who in all the dayes of his life neuer told any lye: In regard whereof the Senate preſently ordained that hee ſhould be made free, and created <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex Maximus:</hi> alſo, that a Statue ſhould be erected for him, and placed amongſt thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:8303:6"/>of the moſt renowned men of all the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. In the dayes of <hi>Claudius,</hi> Emperour likewiſe of Rome, there died a man in Rome named <hi>Pamphylus,</hi> who neuer told any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of truth in all his life time, but euermore had his chiefe delight in lying, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Emperour to giue commaund, that no graue ſhould be graunted to his body, but his goods were confiſcated, his houſe ruined, and his wife and children baniſhed out of Rome, to the end that no memory might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine of ſo venemous a beaſt.</p>
               <p>If the ſame order were among the Papall Frye ſtill in force, wee might hope, that either wee ſhould haue more Truth-tellers, or fewer I yers: But that cuſtome is now aboliſhed, and this vice of Lying raignes more among theſe Maſſe-monging Prieſts, then any people vnder Heauen: Witneſſe thoſe many lyes which they tell of their Saints<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as for example: Saint <hi>Denis</hi> the <hi>Areopagite,</hi> (ſay-they) tooke vp his head after it was ſtricken off, and carried it in his hand two miles. They ſay further, that Saint <hi>Bernac</hi> turned Oke leaues into loaues, ſtones into Fiſhes, water into Wine, and that he ſayled ouer the Sea vpon a ſtone, as an hundred and fifty of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea's</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8303:6"/>company did vpon his ſonnes Shirt, and Fryer <hi>Herueus</hi> vpon his Mantle. They goe on, and tell you, that Saint <hi>Nicholas</hi> whileſt hee lay in his cradle, faſted Wedneſdayes, and Fridayes, on which da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſucke aboue once. They report more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, That Biſhop <hi>Tryan</hi> hauing killed his Cow and his Calfe to entertaine Saint <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricke</hi> and his company, found both of them the next morning feeding in the meadow. They further tell of Saint <hi>Dominickes</hi> books, how they fell into a Riuer, lay there three dayes, and ſo many nights, but were found afterward by a Fiſherman, and taken vp as drie as a feather. They ſay farther, that Saint <hi>Romuala</hi> deliuered high poynts of Diuinity as ſoone as he was borne, and preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that hee was baptized, made a learned Sermon. They deliuer alſo, that Saint <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> being ſwallowed by a Dragon, had no ſooner made the ſigne of the Croſſe; but the Dragon burſt aſunder, and out ſhee came as ſound as a Trout. They ſay alſo, that a man who neuer ſaw further then the length of his noſe, opening <hi>Xauiers</hi> Tombe, and rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing his eyes with his hand ſtraightway re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered his ſight. Yea, they are not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to affirme, that <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> was rapt
<pb facs="tcp:8303:7"/>vp into heauen, and ſaw the holy Trinity in three Perſons, and one Eſſence, and that God ſhewed him the paterne of the world which he layd before him when he made it. They report alſo, that Frier <hi>Bennet</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reZZe</hi> being caſt into the Sea in a Tempeſt, was inuironed with a little cloud, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the terreſtriall Paradiſe, whom when <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaw, they demaunded of him what hee was? And when they heard he was Saint <hi>Francis</hi> his brother, they dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for ioy, and led him about to ſhew him euery corner of Paradiſe; from whence hee was carryed backe againe ouer the Sea in a little Cloud, which marueilouſly aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed thoſe that beheld it. They goe on ſtill, and would make you beleeue that one time, whileſt Saint <hi>Dunſton</hi> was at his deuotion, the Deuill looked in at the windowe, in the ſhape of a beautifull Damſell, thinking to allure him to luſt: but he hating ſuch ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable filthineſſe, tooke the ſaid Deuill by the noſe with a paire of hote tongs. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe they heere ceaſe, but tell won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſurpaſſing credit, of Saint <hi>Thomas Bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket:</hi> For they auerre, That when <hi>Ail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ardus</hi> for ſtealing of a great Whetſtone, (which the Authour that writes it beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued)
<pb facs="tcp:8303:7"/>was by ſentence of Law depriued of his eyes, and virilities, vpon prayer to Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> he had all reſtored againe: Yea, euen a bird hauing beene taught to ſpeake, flying out of her Cage, and now ready to be ſeazed on by a Sparrow-Hawke, ſayd onely, Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> helpe me, and her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my fell preſently dead, but ſhe eſcaped, and (belike) reported it: Yea, in his life time the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> her ſelfe was contented to bee his Sempſter, and ſowed his ſhirt with red Silke.</p>
               <p>But theſe forgeries be onely fit for Monks to indite, Children to reade, and Fooles to beleeue, inuented at the firſt to deceiue poore ignorant people, who cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this their abhominable lying, being nuzled and foſtered all their life long in Ignorance, by a commaund from his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, leaſt they ſhould deſcry their intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable wickedneſſe. And therefore I will not dwell any longer vpon this poynt, but conclude it with a proofe of their Lying: for in the Raigne of King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, King of England, their lying was growne to ſuch a paſſe, that it was held as good an Argument to reaſon thus, <hi>Hic eſt Frater, Ergo Mendax,</hi> He is a Frier,
<pb facs="tcp:8303:8"/>and therefore a Lyer; as to ſay, <hi>Hoc eſt Album, Ergo coloratum:</hi> This thing is white, and therefore coloured.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Their Gluttonie, and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto we haue ſeene them ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, now let vs ſee them wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king like the tops of trees, toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to and fro with the winde. Let vs alſo view their Gu man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing and Glttony. That theſe vices are not wanting in them, is euidently proued by that prayer of theirs to their good Saint <hi>Dominicke,</hi> which runnes thus:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sanctus Dominicus, ſis nobis ſemper amicus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cui canimus noſtro jugiter praeconia roſtro,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>De cordis venis, ſiccatis ante Lagenis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ergo tuas laudes, ſi tu nos pangere gaudes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tempore Paſchali, fac ne potu puteali</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conueniat vti, namſi fiat, vndique muti,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Semper erunt fratres, qui nil curant niſi ventres.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Take him alſo for a witneſſe, who ſaith,
<pb facs="tcp:8303:2"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If that I muſt in order tell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What vertues 'long to Monkiſh Cell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He is not fit for Cell or Couen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That's not a Glutton and a Slouen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sluggiſh, Lecherous, for nought fit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A drunkard, dolt, deuoyd of wit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He muſt eate at each Repaſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vntill his belly well nigh braſt:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hee muſt guzzell in the wine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till he be drunken as a Swine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And if he can but chaunt it well,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This man is fit for Quier or Cell.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And him who ſaith of them,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O Monachi Stomachi veſtri</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ſunt amphora Bacchi,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vos eſtis, Deus eſt teſtis, turpiſsima peſtis.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Take his teſtimony likewiſe, who ſaith of their Monkes:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Si prandet, competit vt loqui neſciat,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ne lingua dentium opus impediat:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Si bibit, expedit vt bibens hauriat,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ne pes ſub pondere ventris deficiat.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Die deuotus adorat dolia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nocte cum bipede laborat beſtia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tali diſcrimine, tali moleſtia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Meretur vir Dei Regna Caeleſtia.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:3"/>
               <p>But becauſe I will not bee too tedious in ſo plaine a caſe as this is, I will conclude this poynt alſo, with that Epigram which was made vpon Saint <hi>Anthonie,</hi> the Saint for Swine:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diceris</hi> Antoni <hi>porcos pauiſſe ſubulcus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivus; adhuc Monachos luminecaſſus alis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Par ſtupor ingenij eſt, ventriſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> abdomen vtriſq</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sorde pari gaudent, ingluvie<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> pari.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nec minus hoc brutum genus eſt, matumue ſuillo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nec minus inſipidum, nec minus illepidum.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cetera conueniunt, ſed non leuis error in vno eſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Debuerat Monachis glans cibus eſſe tuis.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Engliſhed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Once fedſt thou</hi> Anthony <hi>an herd of Swine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And now an heard of Monks thou feedeſt ſtill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For wit and gut alike they both haue bin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Both doe loue filth alike: both like to fill</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The greedy paunch alike: nor is that kind</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>More beaſtly ſottiſh, ſwiniſh then the laſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All elſe agree, one fault J onely find,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou feedeſt not thy Monkes with Oken Maſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Thus much for their Gluttony and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:3"/>
               <head>Their Lecherie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter Gluttony and Drunkenneſſe, followe neceſſarily Lechery and wantonneſſe: and therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we haue prooued them immea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable Drunkards, we may alſo conclude, that they are intolerable licentious, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely addicted to the luſt of the fleſh. And that they are in this vice nothing infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, or leſſe expert, then in their Lying, or Drunkenneſſe, the many bones of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren found about Monaſteries, may bee a ſufficient witneſſe: yet that wee may not be deficient in examples, take theſe as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of their Fornicating: An Abbateſſe in <hi>Lombardie</hi> riſing haſtily from a Prieſt, (with whom ſhee had layne that night) to take a Nun with her Paramour, put on the Prieſts Breeches, in ſtead of her Vaile, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her head, which the poore Nun percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, deſired her firſt to tye the ſtrings of her Coyfe, and then to ſpeake. The Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bateſſe perceiuing her errour, changed the copie of her countenance, and departed.
<pb facs="tcp:8303:4"/>Take another example or two. A certaine Franciſcan in a Towne of Perigrod at the marriage of his Hoſts daughter, cauſed meat to bee ſerued into his Chamber, for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his fellow Fryer, making ſcruple to ſit at the Table with the reſt of the Gueſts, yet made no Conſcience after Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to goe to bedd with the Bride in humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, taking the ſame paines with her in charitie, which he knew the Bridegroome meant to take: Yea, euen their holy Saints, whom ſo religiouſly they adore, are not free from this vice, which wee may prooue by the Tale of that Nun, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a ſore thigh, beſought Saint <hi>Dominicke,</hi> that ſhee might be reſtored to her limbes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; Falling aſleepe, ſhe thought ſhe ſaw Saint <hi>Dominicke</hi> cloſe by her, taking from vnder his Cope a ſtrong ſmelling Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherewith hee annoynted her thigh. And when ſhee asked him what it was, hee told her, that it was called, <hi>The Oyntment of Lone:</hi> which we may vnderſtand to be the priuate familiaritie which was betwixt them. In the time of Pope <hi>Paulus</hi> the third, the number of Whores which were in his Regiſter, amounted to fortie and fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; and yet this was but a ſmall number,
<pb facs="tcp:8303:8"/>compared with that which was before this Popes time. His Holineſſe himſelfe is many times giuen to this vice, as we may perceiue by the Epitaph of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt his daughter, which runnes after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conditur hoc tumulo,</hi> Lucretia <hi>nomine, ſed re,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thais: Alexandri <hi>filia, ſponſa, nurus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Engliſhed thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here lies</hi> Lucrece <hi>in name,</hi> Thais <hi>in life,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Popes child and ſpouſe, and yet his owne ſons wife.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>If then the Popes be thus, how can wee expect that his Cardinalls ſhould be better? Surely they are as ill as their Maſter: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Popes holy Cardinall, <hi>Iohannes Cremenſis,</hi> who being ſent by <hi>Honorius</hi> the ſecond hither into England, in the dayes of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, to redreſſe the ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming abuſe of the Cleargie, in retaining and vſing according to Gods owne Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the ſocietie of their wiues; vpon the birth day of the bleſſed Virgin, made a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Oration in praiſe of Virginitie and Chaſtitie, with a terrible Inuectiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt maried Prieſts; and to amplifie their
<pb facs="tcp:8303:9"/>ſinne the more, hee ſhewed what extreame impietie it was to riſe from the bed of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull luſt, (for ſo was their chaſte marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age tearmed) and with polluted hands to touch the Sacrament of the Body of Chriſt, but the ſame night following, hee hauing that very day conſecrated that holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was himſelfe taken with a whoore. If the Popes Holineſſe, and his reuerend Cardinalls be thus wicked, wee cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that the Minorites, or pettie fiue far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Fryers ſhould bee any whit better? If the root bee vnſound, how can the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches flouriſh? Aſſuredly they follow the ſteps of their Superiours, as in all other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo in this of Lechery more eſpecially, witneſſe him who ſaith:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Proh dolor? hos tolerare poteſt Eccleſia porcos</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Duntaxat ventri, Veneri, ſomno<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> vacantes?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Witneſſe alſo him who ſaith of their holy Fathers in generall:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Noctu filium veneris agitant in cubili,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mane filium Virginis ſacrificant in Altari</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nocte Venerem amplexantur,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mane Virginem venerantur.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:9"/>
               <p>Take his teſtimonie alſo, who ſaith of them:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You Iacobines, Carmelies, Cordeliers,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You Auguſtines, and all you fornicating Friers,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How came you by the ghoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ly fathers names:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For vnder the Crucifixe and high Altars,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You are wont to get vs ſonnes and daughters,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In kind acquaintance with our ghoſtly Dames.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But leaſt they ſhould ſay, that theſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies haue been deuiſed by men of our Profeſsion, to diſgrace them and theirs let vs heare what <hi>Mantuan,</hi> one of their owne Sect ſaith of them:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I pudor in villas ſi non patiuntur eaſdem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et villae vomicas; Roma eſt jam tota Lupaner.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And another of their owne Profeſsion witneſſeth, that the firſt prey which Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſought for when they entred any Towne, was Prieſts Lemmans: But this their Lechery was dearely bought and well paide for; when <hi>Mounſieur d' Avanchi</hi> a French man, admitted two Franciſcans into his Caſtle, made them good Cheere, and to make an end of their kinde entertainment:
<pb facs="tcp:8303:10"/>Hee told them he would pleaſure either of them with his pretty wench. They refuſing his kind offer at the firſt, he requeſted them to make bold with him, telling them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that hee well conſidered they were but fleſh and blood as other men were. In the end he locked them all into a chamber to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and returning thither about an houre after, hee asked them howe they had done; and vnderſtanding that they had not beene idle: O wicked Hypocrites, ſaid hee, is this the way to ouercome temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? and hauing ſo ſaid, hee ſtripped them as naked as my naile, and hauing whipped them as long as himſelfe and men could lay on load, he ſent them away all naked as they were, to teach them to fight another time more valiantly againſt ſuch temptations, or not to giue them the encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter. One of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis Berengers</hi> Chaplaines alſo in <hi>Italy</hi> paid deare for his pleaſure, when being taken and ſtripped naked for playing naught with his Miſtris, he loſt that part wherewith he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended: Let this ſuffice to haue ſpoken of their lewd, and licentious liuing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:10"/>
               <head>Their Couetouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt are they cleere or free from Couetouſneſſe? nothing leſſe. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe their wandring from place to place, and crauing the beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of thoſe people, whom they farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in wealth: Witneſſe alſo that auncient Diſticke.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eſt nullum Monacho majus Daemonium,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nihil auarius, nil magis varium.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cui ſi quid datur eſt poſſeſſor omnium,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si quicquam petitur, nil habet proprium.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Witneſſe likewiſe that Epigram.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Curia vult marcas, burſas exhaurit &amp; arcas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si Burſae parcas, fuge Papas &amp; Patriarchas:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si dederis marcas, et jis impleveris arcas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Culpa ſolveris, quam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ligatus eris.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>And this.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>—<hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enalia Romae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Templa, ſacerdotes, altaria, ſacra, coronae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ignis, thura, preces, Caelum eſt venale, Deus<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:11"/>
               <p>Engliſhed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prieſts, Churches, Altars, holy things,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prayers, Franckincenſe and Crownes of Kings:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yea Heauen and God himſelfe for gold,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At</hi> Rome <hi>is to be bought and ſold.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>And that,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Intus quis? tu quis? ego ſum, quid quaeris? vt intrem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fers aliquid? non, ſta, fero, quid? ſatis intra.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Witnes alſo that made of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vendit</hi> Alexander <hi>claues, altaria, Chriſtum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Emerat ille priùs, vendere jure poteſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Engliſhed,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſt, Altars, Keyes, doth</hi> Alexander <hi>ſell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Why ſhould he not? for why, they coſt him well.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>When King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt his Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, told the Pope that his Maſter would not looſe his right in the Inveſtitures of the Church for the loſſe of his Kingdome. The Pope anſwered, I will not ſuffer him to inioy them without puniſhment, no not for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of my head. This made one brand them
<pb facs="tcp:8303:11"/>with this marke, that the clemencie of the Papall See is neuer wanting to any ſo long as the Red and the White make interceſſion for them.</p>
               <p>Their Auarice may alſo be ſeene in their Indulgences, Pardons, Maggot-eaten Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, Paxes, Crucifixes, Trentals, Dirges, Pictures of Saints, Bulls, hallowed Beanes, Holy water, Exorciſmes, and a thouſand ſuch fables and bables, which were too long and too weariſom a taske to relate, all which are inuented for no other end and purpoſe, but by drawing money from the poore Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norants, to fill and ſtuffe the Popes Coffers. We may alſo call to witneſſe their couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that beſt Fire in the Popes Kitchin, Purgatory, which was found out for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but that poore people not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing to the contrary, might giue lands and liuings to theſe Maſſe-monging Prieſts, to the end that they by ſaying ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Maſſes, Dirges, <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> and the like for their ſoules, might rid them out of that (as they thinke) fearefull place. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point with that of the Poet:
<q>—<hi>Heu Romae, nunc ſola pecunia regnat.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:12"/>
               <head>Their Blasphemie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eere my haire ſtartles, and my Pen is euen ready to fall out of my hand, conſidering the many execrable and abominable blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies which their hearts haue conceiued, their mouthes vttered, yea, and their hands committed to writing: to ſuch a height are they growne of impietie, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and wreſting Scriptures (like a noſe of waxe) to their owne ends, and applying thoſe things to themſelues, which were meant of Chriſt. <hi>Alexander</hi> the third hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Emperour <hi>Fredericke</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate himſelfe, and aske him pardon for his offences; the Emperour kneeled: This gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Pope, ſetting his foot vpon his throat, or (as ſome ſay) vpon his necke, moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly applyed thoſe wordes to himſelfe, which were vnderſtood of Chriſt, <hi>It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Thou ſhalt walke vpon the Aspe and the Baſiliske, the young Lyon and the Dragon ſhalt thou tread vnder thy feete.</hi> The Emperour highly offended for this contempt, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:8303:12"/>I doe not this to thee, but to Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> The Pope treading vpon him the ſecond time, ſaid, <hi>Et mihi, &amp; Petro,</hi> Both to me and to Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one of his Cardinalls preach, who chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Text out of the New Teſtament, burſt foorth into theſe execrable blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous words, O what great Riches haue wee got by this Fable of Chriſt? Pope <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the third louing a Peacocke very well, and miſsing it one time from his Table, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked where it was? Anſwere was made, That his Phyſicions had giuen charge hee ſhould eate none, becauſe it was preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to his health. He being moſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly bent, preſently replies, Fetch mee my Peacocke, <hi>Ce dispetto de Dio.</hi> When his Cardinalls, and other followers beſought him not to bee ſo angry, hee ſtill perſeuers in his impietie, and anſweres them, If God were ſo angry for an Apple, as that hee caſt our firſt parents out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, why may not I who am his Vicar, be thus angry for a Peacocke, which is a greater matter then an Apple.</p>
               <p>A Prieſt of Lorraine holding a Pixe or boxe full of vnconſecrated ſinging Cakes, (as they tearme them) ſhuffled them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:8303:13"/>ſaying, Yee little Whoreſons, ye lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Whoreſons, which of you will bee God to day? One praying to our Lady holding her young Babe in her armes, (whom ſo reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly they adore and worſhip) and hauing receiued ſuch an anſwer as pleaſed him not, by one that ſtood behind the Image, and iudging by the voyce that it was the Child that ſpake, ſaid, Hold your peace, and let your Mother ſpeake, who is wiſer then you. Yea, they are not content thus blaſphemouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to abuſe God and his diuine Word, but they muſt boaſt alſo of this their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>And are not (I pray you) their prayings to Saints, yea worſe then that, to ſtockes and ſtones, ſo many blaſphemies againſt Gods ſacred Maieſtie? Is it not a moſt execrable blaſphemy, to make our Lady equall, yea, aboue our Sauiour? making him but a halfe, yea, no Sauiour at all.</p>
               <p>If this bee not Blaſphemy in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree, I would gladly know what it is? But let them take heed, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with whome they haue to doe, when thus they mocke GOD, euen with him whoſe eyes cannot behold Iniquitie, but will repay the committers thereof. This
<pb facs="tcp:8303:13"/>ſinne of Blaſphemy hath hee in all ages pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the higheſt degree. Witneſſe <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> a notorious blaſphemer of Chriſtes Diuinitie, who was deuoured with dogs. <hi>Arrius</hi> had ſuch a looſeneſſe of belly, that hee voyded his Intrailes. <hi>Lewes</hi> the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, King of Fraunce, beholding cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Tennis-players, with his wife, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other talke, ſaid, Hee hoped to doe nothing hereafter which ſhould offend GOD: which words were no ſooner out of his mouth, but hee fell downe ſpeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and languiſhing a few houres, dyed in the ſame place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sophocles</hi> writeth, That before <hi>Aiax</hi> went to the Siege of Troy, his father counſelled him to fight valiantly, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to pray to GOD for Victory, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aiax</hi> anſwered, <hi>Adiutore Deo, vel ignavus vincere poteſt, Ego ſine Deo.</hi> And therefore God ſmote him with a Frenzie, ſo that hee went about the field, ſlaying the ſilly Sheepe and Cattell, ſuppoſing that they had been his enemies; and when this was done, hee kills himſelfe on the point of his owne Sword.</p>
               <p>One in an Inne laughing at thoſe which
<pb facs="tcp:8303:14"/>ſpoke of Chriſt, offered to ſell his ſoule for a cup of Wine: one hauing bought it off him, the Deuill being among them like a Swaggerer, bought it at the ſecond hand, and then making challenge of his Bargaine, hurryed him away with him in the ayre, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which time he was neuer ſeene.</p>
               <p>Certaine Gameſters at Mantua breaking foorth into blaſphemy againſt our bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sauiour, their eyes fell on the Table. And a childe at Rome not aboue fiue yeares of age, blaſpheming the Name of God, was carryed away by the Deuill, from betweene his parents armes. And a Marriner at Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouſe, moſt fearefully tearing and rending GOD aſunder with his bloudie Oathes, fell into the Sea, and was not ſeene, till certaine dayes after, that hee was found on the Shoare, where his Bodie was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp intire and whole, the Tongue one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted.</p>
               <p>And that I may not bee too tedious in a poynt ſo euident, wee may ſee it in the two Popes afore-mentioned, <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth and <hi>Iulius</hi> the third; the firſt of which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer-ioyed for a Victory receiued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the French, reuelled three dayes
<pb facs="tcp:8303:14"/>and ſo many nights together, and then dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Drunkenneſſe: The latter of them came moſt miſerably to a ſhamefull end.</p>
               <p>Seeing then this ſinne neuer eſcapes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed, what hope can theſe Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers haue? Doe they thinke God is not ſo iuſt, or more mercifull then heretofore hee hath beene? Or doe they thinke hee ſleepes, or winkes, and will not ſee their impietie? It is blaſphemy to thinke either. Let them therefore eyther amend, or elſe looke for the like, or more fearefull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But I haue beene (I feare) too long in this poynt, and therefore I will conclude it with that of the Poet <hi>Virgil.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Diſcite Iuſtiam moniti, &amp; non temnere Diuos.</hi>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:15"/>
               <head>Their Pride.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the pride of theſe Pedlers of Reliques is no leſſe, then their fore-named Vices, may ſufficiently appeare, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the many Titles, which that great Vicar, (as hee ſtiles himſelfe) of Chriſt, arrogates to himſelfe, ſetting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aboue Kings and Emperours, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to hold his Stirrop; yea, euen to put their neckes as a Foot-ſtoole for him to tread vpon, putting on Crownes with his foote, and caſting them downe with it againe as ſoone as put on, and making Kings, with their Wiues and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to ſtand three dayes together at his Gate barefoot and barelegged, and there to wayt till his Holineſſe be pleaſed to giue them abſolution.</p>
               <p>Their Triple-Crowne alſo is no leſſe an Argument of their pride, as is alſo their challenging to themſelues both Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall and Temporall Authoritie: Euen
<pb facs="tcp:8303:15"/>
                  <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelfe is not more proud then is his Holineſſe, who holdes out his foot to bee kiſſed by the greateſt Monarchs: One time as hee was ſtretching it out to bee kiſſed by an Emperour, a Spaniell got hold of it, and bit it: And therefore his Holineſſe loſt the Reuerence at that time, which ſhould haue beene done vnto him, becauſe the Emperour refuſed to kiſſe that place which a Dogge had bitten. But they will tell you perhaps, that this reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is not done to them, but to the Croſſe which is ſet vpon his Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe: But this argues a great deale more pride, in that they dare put ſo ſacred a thing (as they holde the Croſſe to bee) vpon their ſhooe, which ſeemes to bee but a contemptible, and vile place, and not rather in ſome more eminent part of the body, as Head, breaſt, or the like.</p>
               <p>Their being carryed on mens ſhoulders, as though the ground were not good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for them to tread vpon, is a moſt manifeſt argument, that this Vice doth raigne in them, and yet (forſooth) the whole World muſt bee guided by them, and ſubmit themſelues to their commaunds:
<pb facs="tcp:8303:16"/>They muſt bee ſupreame Biſhops, chiefe Lordes, greateſt Comptrollers of States; and eyther all men muſt obey, and ſtoope at their becke, or elſe out comes a Bull preſently to excommunicate them, as late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it did againſt our late Queene, now Saint <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in which they pronounce her an Heretique, and an Alien from the Common-wealth of Iſrael. Each Fiue-far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Shaueling muſt bee reuerenced and obſerued as if hee were ſome great man. One of their Profeſſion, a Cardinall, made a Feaſt to <hi>Eleanor</hi> of <hi>Arragon,</hi> wherein were ſo many ſeuerall ſorts of meates, and daintie Diſhes, that it laſted for the ſpace of ſeauen houres: and leaſt his Gheſtes ſhould haue beene wearyed, hee cauſed ſundrie Playes to bee acted, whileſt they were at the Table. And to make his pride compleate, hee cauſed euery Seruitour at euery new Courſe, to come in a new Suite. Yet all this is nothing to the pride hee ſhewed to his Concubine <hi>Tireſia,</hi> for hee kept her publikely in ſuch ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner, that her very Shooes were ſet full of Pearles and precious Stones. Yet theſe men muſt bee accounted the
<pb facs="tcp:8303:16"/>onely Meeke, Humble, Gentle, and Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men vpon earth: but if theſe things I haue reckoned vp, ſauour any thing of humilitie, let any equall Arbitrator bee Iudge: for mine owne part, I cannot ſee that any humble man will exalt himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his Superiours, as the Pope doth.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the Monke was ſent into Brittaine from Rome, to teach the Britaines Chriſtianitie, it is written, that the Brittaines went firſt to a certaine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wiſe man, (which liued an Anchorites life) to aske his counſell, whether they ought at <hi>Auſtens</hi> Preaching and exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to leaue their Traditions or not? The Anchorite replyes, If hee bee a man of God, follow him. But how ſhall wee prooue (ſay they) that he is a man of God? The Anchorite anſwered, If hee bee mild and humble of heart, then hee is a man of God; If curſt and proud, hee is not of GOD, neither muſt you much eſteeme his words. They inquire how they might know, whether he were proud or no? If (quoth he) when you come neere him, hee ariſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and ſalute you, then thinke him to be a Seruant of Chriſt, and ſo heare him
<pb facs="tcp:8303:17"/>and obey him: if hee deſpiſe you, and will not vouchſafe to riſe at your preſence, let him likewiſe be deſpiſed of you. They go to him, where they finde him ſet in his Chaire, but ſtirred not: which when they ſaw, forthwith waxing wroth, they noted him of Pride; and therefore endeauored to thwart and gaineſay whatſoeuer he propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and ſo the preaching of the Goſpell was put off, till a man of better temper ſhould come. Thus in part haue we ſeene the pride and the arrogancy of theſe Shaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, in ſome ſmall manner layd open to the world, but I may ſay as <hi>Virgil</hi> ſayd in an other caſe:</p>
               <q>Non mihi ſi centum linguae ſint oraque centum Ferrea vox, &amp;c.</q>
               <p>Though I had a thouſand mouthes, and euery mouth ſo many tongues; though I had a Stentorian voyce, which would neuer faile, yet were I not able to reckon vp the one halfe of their pride.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:17"/>
               <head>Their wickedneſſe in generall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET vs nowe ſpeake a little of their wickedneſſe in generall, and ſo an ende: And nrſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Demy-God the Pope: When <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth was reprooued by certaine of his Cardinalls for his looſe and wicked life, hee anſwered, If I be wicked, I may thank you for it: for you made me ſuch a one as I am. They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding of him what he meant thereby, he anſweres, Becauſe you made mee Pope: for it is not poſsible to bee both a Pope and an honeſt man.</p>
               <p>When certaine asked <hi>Paſquin,</hi> what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury had been done him, becauſe hee loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked not after his accuſtomed manner; hath any man called thee Thiefe, Murderer, Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, or the like? Hee anſwered, Oh no, but they haue calleo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me worſe. What? hath any man called thee Sacrilegious perſon,
<pb facs="tcp:8303:18"/>or Buggerer, Parricide, or Atheiſt? Oh no, (ſaith hee) but they haue called me worſe. In the end, being often requeſted to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his griefe, breathing out many ſighes, with, Alas, Alas, hee ſayd, they had called him <hi>POPE.</hi> The ſame <hi>Paſquin</hi> made this Epigram, or (if thou wilt) Epitaph vpon this word Pope.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hic Carapha jacet, ſuperis inuiſus &amp; imis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Styx animam, tellus putre cadauer habet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inuidit pacem terris, Dijs vota preceſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Impius &amp; Clerum perdidit &amp; populum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoſtibus infenſis ſupplex, infidus amicis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scire cupis paucis cetera? PAPA fuit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hildebrand</hi> poyſoned ſeauen or eight Popes, that hee might come to the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Joan</hi> was taken for Pope <hi>Iohn,</hi> till ſhee was deliuered of her great belly; ſince which time they haue gotten a bottomleſſe Chaire, through which they were wont to ſearch the Popes humanitie. But nowe they haue left that Cuſtome, hauing giuen ſufficient teſtimony of their virilitie before they come to aſcend the Papall Throne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:18"/>
               <p>Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> (as I take it) the eighth, crept in like a Foxe, reigned like a Wolfe, and dyed like a Dog.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the Head, let vs now deſcend a little lower, and ſearch if the members bee any whitt better, and wee ſhall finde them ſimpathize all with the Head: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: If the head bee vnſound, the whole body muſt needs bee ill at eaſe. If the Popes Holineſſe be thus wicked, the people whom they hold to bee altogether vnholy, muſt needes bee farre worſe. They will Sweare, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare, Curſe, Blaſpheame, Fornicate, Kill, Dare to doe any villanie; and why? His Holineſſe doth it, and why not wee? That which is good for him, cannot bee hurtfull to vs: and therefore we will doe it: If need bee, wee can goe to him, and get a Pardon, and when wee haue done, ſinne againe, and get a Pardon; and at our death giue but ſo much to a deuoute Monke, to ſay ſo many Dirges, and chaunt ſo many Maſſes, and we ſhall be in as happy an eſtate as the beſt.</p>
               <p>Hence come thoſe many Powder-plots, Poyſons, Poyniards, Gunnes, Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="tcp:8303:19"/>Croyſadoes, Rackes, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more ſuch diuelliſh things, inuented by the Pope and his Monkes, and put in practiſe by your Laytie. But Oh poore ſoules, why doe you ſuffer your ſelues to bee thus ſeduced and miſſe-led by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in the likeneſſe and ſhape of a man? Looke but narrowly with the eye of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion into his actions, and you ſhall ſee how you are deceiued: Weigh our two Religions in an equall ballance, and ſee if yours bee not too light. Thinke vpon that Epigram:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eſſe Lutheranum rumorte Gaurice clamat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed tuus Antiſtes te tamen eſſe negat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tam ſcortaris (ait) quam ſi vel Epiſcop us eſſes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et potus dubium peruigit vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> diem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec memor es Chriſti, niſi cum jurare libeb it,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec ſis Scripturae vel breue jotu ſacrae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nempe per haec ſueuit numquam fallentia ſigna,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ille vigill ſanas noſcere paſtor oues.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Heere you may ſee the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two Religions, whether of them ſweares, blaſphemes, curſes, whores, drinkes, reuells, and the like, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:8303:19"/>of them feares to doe theſe things; Iudge of them, and as you finde them, ſo follow them. Let vs now ſpeake a little of their holy Fathers. Heare what one ſaith of their Cardinals:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Semiviros quicunque patres radiante galero,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conspicis &amp; rubrae ſyrmata longa togae.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Crede mihi nullo ſaturatas murice veſtes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diuite nec cocco pallia tincta vides.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sed quae rubra vides, Sanctorum caede virorum</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et merſa inſonti tota cruore madent.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aut memor iſtorum quae celet crimina veſtis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pro Dominis juſto tacta pudore rubet.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Another ſpeaking of their Prieſts, ſaith, that they are <hi>Angeli Sathanae per diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam, Angeli Apoſtatici per ſuperbiam, Angeli Jncubi per Luxuriam, Angeli Abyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi per Auaritiam:</hi> And another ſayeth of their Monkes:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Credibile eſt Circen, mutaſſe potentibus herbis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Monachoſque Sues, inque Sues Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachos.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:20"/>
               <p>Engliſhed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It's like that Circe with her Spels diuine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hath turned Swine to Monkes, and Monkes to Swine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fulco</hi> a French Prieſt comming to King <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, told him hee had three very badde daughters, which hee wiſhed him to beſtowe away from him in marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, or elſe Gods wrath would attend him. When the King denyed hee had any daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Prieſt anſwered, Yes, thou haſt three Daughters, Pride, Couetouſneſſe, and Lecherie. The King apprehenſiue of his meaning, replyed, My Pride I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath to the haughtie Templers and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitallers, who are as proude as <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelfe: My Couetouſneſſe I giue to the White Monkes of <hi>Ciſteaux</hi> Order, for they couet the Deuill and all. And as for my Lecherie, I can beſtowe it no where bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then on the Prieſtes and Prelates of our times, for therein haue they their moſt felicitie.</p>
               <p>Theſe proud, conetous, Lecherous, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing
<pb facs="tcp:8303:20"/>Fryers and Monkes did ſo domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neere in England in the Raigne of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, that a Cardinall told the Pope, that England was to the Pope like <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe, which being ſo often veron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſpurre-galled, and cudgelled, it was no maruaile if at the length ſhe opened her mouth to complaine: And as for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their Romane Court, they were like vnto <hi>Iſmael,</hi> euery mans hand was againſt them, and theirs againſt euerie man.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Kings Raigne, <hi>Edmund</hi> Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury weary of his life here in his owne Countrey of England, by reaſon that hee could not redreſſe nor ſuppreſſe the Popes deteſtable exactions, and oppreſsions, made choyce of a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary exile at Pountney in Fraunce, where hee dyed with the honour and opinion of a Saint.</p>
               <p>A Senator of Rome ſayd to <hi>Sylla,</hi> that vaunted of himſelfe in the Senate: How can you bee a good man, that hauing lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing left you by you father, yet in ſo ſhort a time are become exceeding rich? So may we ſay to the Popes Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:8303:21"/>vaunting and boaſting, that he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Kings and Emperours, How can you bee a good man, who having (as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) little or nothing, but went about begging the beneuolence of good charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble people, yet now are raiſed to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dignitie, that you ſet your ſelues aboue your Superiours? And wee may ſay of all Papiſts in generall, That they arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate to themſelues the glorious name of Catholiques, and brand their oppoſites with the odious name of Heretiques, as certaine Heathen in old time called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Deiſts, and all men elſe Atheiſts: and as the Turke at this day, who will needs be the true <hi>Muſelman,</hi> and all the world beſide Pagans. But this their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion, is nothing but Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique corruption: and Catholique Papiſts, Catholique Heretiques.</p>
               <p>I will now draw towards a Concluſion, giue mee leaue onely to ſpeake a little of Rome, and ſo an end: In ancient times, <hi>M. Aurelius</hi> ſaid of Rome, that it was the head of vices: O Rome without Rome, which now art become Stewes of vices: not without teares (quoth hee) I ſay, that
<pb facs="tcp:8303:21"/>there was neuer any Romane Captaine, that killed tenne thouſand Aſians, with the weapons hee brought into Aſia, but he loſt an hundred thouſand Romanes with the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they brought to Rome. Thy walles are carryed a great height, but thy vertues ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry low: Shee braggeth of the number of her Inhabitants, but may rather weepe, that her vices be more without compariſon; In one moneth a man may number the ſtones of her ſtately Buildings, but not in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares her lewde manners. O curſed Rome, curſed thou haſt beene, art, and wilt bee: As by thy Tyrannie thou haſt made thy ſelfe Lady of Lordes, ſo the time will come, when thou with Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhalt returne to bee Seruant of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</p>
               <p>The like Sentence another gaue of Rome, who tolde the Senators, that he came out of ſtrange Countries onely to ſee Rome, and now he found it without Rome: If my Iudgement (ſaith he) deceiue me not, either theſe be not Romanes of Rome, or elſe this is not Rome of the Romanes.</p>
               <p>This was Rome in ancient time, and that it is ſtill the ſame, may ſufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb facs="tcp:8303:22"/>by thoſe abuſes of the Inhabitants thereof afore mentioned: And therefore I thinke I may ſafely conclude with that Diſticke of the Poet:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Roma vale, vidi, ſatis eſt vidiſſe, reuertar</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cum Leno, aut meretrix, ſcurra, cynaedus ero.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Engliſhed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now farewell Rome, I haue thee ſeene,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It is enough to ſee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I will returne when as I meane</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bawd, Scoffer, Whore and Rogue to bee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:8303:22"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
